this is the first in a series of films
that we're making looking at what are
the deeper issues that this pandemic and
this growing crisis is bringing up and
this first one is gonna be about
complexity and systems thinking the
systems and complexity people saw it
first because they were actually looking
at how all these different fragilities
across different systems were providing
a perfect storm it was coming and it
happened to be a pandemic it's something
that is being really highlighted with
what's happening right now because we've
had what initially started as a medical
crisis cascading into an economic crisis
whose noting knock-on effect in the
education system and all of these other
systems so what it's doing is really
showing and I think giving people a very
visceral direct experience and what a
lot of systems thinkers and complexity
theorists have been talking about for a
very long time how it's very difficult
to look at anything in isolation because
it's automatically interrelated with
lots of other systems so one thing I've
really noticed is that there's a real
tangible difference between thinking and
talking about complexity and looking at
the models and knowing that
theoretically everything is
interconnected and then the lived
experience of it in our own lives and
I've really noticed that I remember just
you know going to the shop and one of
the kind of every ten day shops that
have been doing and noticing the line
outside and then you know being in the
shop and just being hyper aware of the
fragility of our supply chains you know
starting to wonder how much of this food
is grown in the UK and how much you know
all of those questions become extremely
real and it's for me visceral and I
think many of us were all experiencing
it in real time so what was hidden
before is is now all all being laid bare
and sort of the the underlying source
code of society is suddenly becoming
obvious and clear and one thing we're
noticing is that it is incredibly
fragile and with that comes a huge
question of what do we do and there's
also the question of why our
institutions and our leaders were so
seemingly unprepared seemingly
blindsided by it and I think a lot of
that has to do with not thinking in kind
of terms of complexity in terms of
systems so in this film
three interviews with some amazing
complex thinkers got Jim rut who's the
former chairman of the Santa Fe
Institute Joe Brewer who's kind of made
a name for himself as something of a
collapse ologist and Nora Bateson so
Nora is the daughter of Gregory Bateson
who's a kind of legendary figure from
the 1970s and came up with a lot of the
concepts that are still being used by
people in this area and she's keeping
his work alive through the Bateson
Institute looking at the
interrelatedness of things and something
she calls warm data which is that you
cannot take data out of the system and
make sense of it because it's always
part of a living system on the Gullah
understand it as such and she talked in
the interview about Cassandra which is
the Greek myth about the prophet who was
fated to be right but disbelieved and
what are the key things that maybe we
need to learn from complexity and since
systems thinking that will help us
understand and maybe get out of this
crisis or maybe use this crisis to
transition to something better than the
system that come didn't see it coming in
the first place
you know in particular I could name some
of the people who were the the
Cassandra's in this case and you know
the curse of Cassandra is to be able to
see the future but to have no one
believe you and I think e if you're
looking at multiple systems
simultaneously and complexity thinkers
have been actually as systems thinkers
have been saying for decades I mean not
just right before this but for decades
that there is an incredible destructive
fragility and not just one of our
systems like it's not just the education
system it's not just the economy it's
not just the health care system it's not
just the political system it's it's not
just that the ruled way technology is in
our lives it's all of those systems
simultaneously and more importantly
their fragility is in the relationship
between them
okay so unless there were people who
were kind of composers right people who
are looking at the way all the
instruments in the orchestra are coming
together to form the music what one ends
up seeing is various different scores
for different instruments so you have
experts in health care experts in
education experts in the economy experts
in political work you have
anthropologists you have media and tech
people and everybody is given their
authorisation their credibility by their
expertise in their particular zone and
not very many people were traveling
between those zones and when they were
traveling between them a lot of them
were caught in a kind of need to pay
their own bills and in doing so they
kind of had to provide a way for the
existing system to continue right it was
the the kind of the curse of the systems
thinker that you couldn't walk into an
organization or a Ministry of Health or
the education or the Department of of
whatever and say actually this is
screwed we need to we need to completely
restructure this in conjunction with all
these other people that you never talked
to and that job was impossible to get to
it was just it was just out of reach so
there were a lot of us who have for
decades been saying you know in one way
or another whether it's ecological
crisis or economic crisis or culture
political crisis or a pandemic or a
nuclear war or a hora hora hora like it
could have been any number of systems
systems trigger
and and it in a way now I have to
preface this by saying there are people
that are very dear to my heart who are
in ICU beds right now so I'm not saying
this lightly but I'm really glad that
there is the moment to perceive these
inter systemic fragilities and that the
trajectories of the way all these
different contexts of our world were
going was leading to disaster it always
was so in a way I'm I'm relieved that we
have this and not a nuclear war to wake
us up but that doesn't that doesn't
really give much consolation in the
moment when you're with your I mean I'm
you know having to deal with people who
are right on the edge of life right now
so I I don't I don't I don't say those
words lately and I'm not one for the you
know painting the the gilded glory
moment of oh this is going to be such an
opportunity because I think maybe even
that opportunistic attitude is kind of
harkening a kind of way of perceiving
that lacks the sensitivity that we
actually need to to move into
possibilities that are there we need to
be angry we need to be sad we need to be
awake we need to be broken open all of
us even the systems and complexity
experts write the script all scripts are
not useful now so I guess I'm going on
and on but the system sinking
like city people saw it first because
they were actually looking at how all
these different fragilities across
different systems were providing a
perfect storm and it was something was
gonna was gonna trigger it I think a lot
of people thought it was going to be
ecological disaster or maybe you know
mass migration or food security it was
coming and it happened to be a pandemic
Anora was hinting and there why this is
such a deep crisis it's not just a
crisis of medical system the economic
system it's in some ways a crisis of the
entire Western Way of understanding the
world in this very kind of atomistic
deterministic kind of way and that seems
to be what I think we've been pointing
to since the beginning of the channel
with rebel wisdom it's like no there's a
crisis when the Western Way of looking
at the world and we need to we need to
take a step back we need to actually
think in different ways in some ways
become of different kinds of people to
make sense of the world yeah and
actually just before the crisis we were
exploring this in a lost ways of knowing
and it was that it's not that there's
anything inherently wrong with with
atomizing things and seeing them in that
way it's an important skill to have it's
just that we over rely on that way of
knowing so extremely that it blinds us
both John drove a key and in McGilchrist
who we've we've had in the channel a few
times have different models that explain
why that kind of narrowing of our
perception happens and why it's so
detrimental especially for you know to
draw on what Nora is talking about
zooming out and seeing the whole and
just even the concept of seeing things
as interconnected and provisional even
that isn't really represented very well
in the ways of knowing that we rely on
very heavily for you know for example
science and history very what for vacuum
called propositional it's about knowing
that so they're important but we also
have to have other ways of seeing things
like for example you know Nora talks
about warm data seeing things in context
you know things like aesthetic myth
there's lots of different ways we can
start tapping into different types of
information that that serve as well so
next I spoke to Jim rut who is the
former chairman of the Santa Fe
Institute which is
is one of the places that has really
pioneered complexity research and
systems thinking and he is also very
influential and was actually probably
the prime mover in creating the initial
game B movement which we've talked about
quite a bit on the channel
he brought a load of people together
something actually making a documentary
about at the moment and I interviewed
him back in October last year for the
new for the documentary about game B and
he said this which I think now seems
quite prescient and we talked a little
bit before starting about the fifth
attractor which i think is really really
interesting at the moment when with
there's a whole resurgence of interest
in Game B and in this kind of what
potential system might come next can you
outline that from the beginning so
here's the story of the fifth attractor
using complexity science we can think of
basins of attraction or strange
attractors some people call them so
think about all the things that make our
society what it is our social operating
system think of it being like a metal
bowl and then think a marble in that
bowl as the current state of that system
and the marble rolls around in the bowl
we go from more conservative to more
liberal more Victorian to more
emancipated you know in all kinds of
different so the marble is always moving
around but it's also periodically moving
up the side of the bowl towards the edge
and so far hasn't flowed out if we want
to say our current system started in
1694 the day i happened the year i
happened to give for the start of the
current system it doesn't really matter
you pick other ones but the marble has
never flown out of the bowl since then I
have some reasons to believe that it may
well that whether they're whether that
we reach the limits of our ecosystem
that's one way that the marble could fly
out of the thing very quickly then
there's other ways you look at the ever
growing inequality of wealth and power
in our societies I'm hearing the Clank
of the guillotine more and more every
day or getting to the levels of
inequality and unfairness in our society
or historically people have revolted and
overthrown the powers that be could
easily happen there could be a
resurgence of some religious craziness
right we see surprise
the amount that of that running around
loose in the world it could be a disease
you know we have depleted the the power
of many of our antibiotics there could
be a plague that takes loose and
remember not that long ago you know 14th
century a third to a quarter of the part
to a half the population of Europe died
in the bubonic plague death right the
marble flies out of the bowl where does
it land and this is why I called the
article in search of the fifth attractor
because I believe there are four more
tractors out there for bowls waiting to
catch the marble and all four are worse
than the one we're in today and the four
as I see it our neo-fascism in China
being the exemplars
being not too far from it of authorial
technologically empowered dictatorship
with high levels of control of media and
communications militarism plus
nationalism classic fascism the fact
that Chinese claim to be Marxist
Leninist ignore that story
they are neo-fascists number 2 neo
feudalism I used to be a soft
libertarian but strong forms of
libertarianism I believe are very
similar to feudalism they believe a few
people who happen to own lots and lots
of resources will have utter control
everybody below them the next one is neo
Dark Ages you know the West after the
fall of Rome famously you know fell into
a period where our civilization dropped
many many levels and the fourth is one
that's always with us the possibility of
real chaos and you know true anarchy
where once it easily imagined 90% of the
population on earth dying during the
period when our very deep stack of
technologies is collapsed it's down to a
low level may be the equivalent of 1875
level of technology so for bad
attractors neo-fascism neo feudalism neo
dark ages and chaos so let's I think
good people's a mission should be to
work on building the fifth attractor
before we need it
now we might need it tomorrow afternoon
which case were fucked so Jim we did an
interview back in I think October now
last year where I just listened to it
back and you actually talked about you
talked about the 5th attractor and how
we need to find another stable system
because it's likely that we will need at
some point in the near future and you
actually said in that you mentioned that
a pandemic could be one cause for us
kind of being out of the state that
we're in and needing this new system to
shift to the complexity theorist seem to
be the ones who were predicting
something like this and had some idea of
the kind of the second and third-order
consequences that it might cause this
has been a probably a kind of a wake-up
call for a lot of people and a real
teaching in complexity what are the key
things that people need to know and
people are maybe learning the hard way
right now
key part and again why I had panda Bank
on my list of possible causes is the
concept of fat tails in fact you know
the concept I've written historically
skeptical the concept of wisdom and the
wisdom teachings and all that whoo horse
shit right
however I've now concluded that in our
modern world there is something called
wisdom and it consists of two things
first and above all else understanding
the concept of fat tails and this is
something that comes up again and again
and again in complex systems thinking
particularly about social systems which
is that unlike what seems like unlikely
events are not that unlikely for
instance the financial crisis of 2008 my
blood would just boil when these
financial executives would go on and say
oh this was a one in a million year
event how could we possibly a plan for
it wrong dude if you understand power
law distributions which is a specific
mathematical kind of curve which an
astounding number of social systems
approximate no one should be careful
that didn't say it's not exactly a power
law but it's like it which means that
the the right side of the curve the bad
events happened way more often than a
Gaussian distribution and if we look at
the pandemics over the last 20 years we
had two already three we had SARS we had
MERS and we had a bola
right probably a bunch of other ones I
didn't even track and if you plot those
on a curve how many cases how many
fatalities there on the left part of the
power law distribution but they're much
more happening much more rapidly than a
Gaussian or random distribution would
tell you and so he all it takes is to
think in power laws and you will know
that at the rate at which these things
are popping up a worse one will happen
and oh by the way this is by far not the
worst one that's possible we're not way
out on the right tail
we're probably you know I'm just gonna
guess here and so don't hold me the
mathematical rigor on this we're
probably at about a 1 in 30 or 40 years
probability on the right
side of the distribution considering the
contagiousness of this one which is high
but not super high it's about a third of
measles for instance measles is three
times as contagious it's got a pretty
high kill rate fatality rate on the
order of one to two percent pretty high
for these kinds of things but it could
be higher SARS was six or seven percent
MERS was like fifteen or twenty percent
right something like smallpox is the the
real scary one which is more contagious
than this it kills 50 percent of the
people so this is on the right tail on
the right side of the distribution but
not way out there so this was
predictable in a few if you would
specify the statistical nature of this
epidemic in October when we chatted and
said what do you think Jeff what do you
chances are something like this
happening I've said fuck yeah it'll
definitely happen and probably in my
lifetime and I'm an old fart with only
you know a life expectancy of 25 years
or thereabout so yeah so that's where if
one thinks in power laws and and fat
tails one is at the first step of wisdom
and the second specifically the
pandemics and again I'll Pat myself on
the back you know I called my family
into our Mountain stronghold our farm
four weeks ago we're then when people
were saying you're overreacting what the
hell dude and I said you don't
understand Exponential's and if you
understand Exponential's and combine
that with fat tails in this current
world you're approximating what people
might call wisdom I also spoke to Joe
Brewer who we haven't had on the channel
before that he's very well regarded and
known by a lot of the people we have the
people like Daniel Shmack Tim burger and
he is trying basically to bring together
the worlds of complexity research
cognitive science and cultural evolution
he's kind of made a name for himself as
something of a collapse ologist
if such word exists and you've been
talking about this stuff for a long time
been looking at it for a long time what
is your sense
now how do you feel the sort of cultural
shift in terms of people taking this
seriously now in the wake of this and in
sort of as we start to project out
further forward one thing that I see is
that more people are recognizing
interdependencies or what Fritjof Capra
calls the state of interbeing the
recognition that my existence depends on
the existence of others and that's
really potent when you might go outside
and get sick or make someone sick
so this feeling I don't care if they
have the name for it people are getting
it and so one thing I see is that people
are feeling that and they're slowing
down when most of them have not
practiced slowing down now those of us
who already made changes in our lives
before this we're thriving in a way that
most of our friends are now recognizing
that we made good choices so like my
friends at see me making smoothies with
fresh vegetables because I moved to a
place where there's a campus you know
culture and then the tropics and there's
actually a food web of support they see
that I'm getting healthy food and I
don't have to go to the grocery store
they're like maybe Joe understands it
and I think a lot of us have someone in
our networks who did something like this
so one thing that I see is a relaxing of
the rigidity a humility of perspective
for people who realize that they
actually don't know what to do they also
are realizing no one is telling them to
make a decision and so they're in this
place where they can introspect and I'm
very hopeful about that I think that
could with the right nudging with the
right supports with the right
conversations a true transformation is
possible I don't think it's likely I get
less than 50 percent I'd even say less
than 10 percent likely we would achieve
a transformation in this moment in these
few months but in some places it will
happen because of this opportunity and
so everyone that is in a place of trying
to create the changes try to help your
friends understand better how they can
make the changes and everyone is in
these moments of pause and
eugen use this as an opportunity to
educate yourself some more about how you
might live differently and don't let me
tell you a damn thing about how to live
differently if at the time as jordan
green hall has said this is time for
sovereignty make your own damn decisions
and maybe for once in your life make
your own damn decisions because we've
been told what to do by our employers
and by our customers for so long we have
this opportunity and so that's where I
think um yes pandemic as ever as a
blessing and decide and disguise if we
will receive the gift and why do you
think so few of us saw this coming or at
least certainly the institutions and the
policymakers and the people who were
supposed to be in charge I was supposed
to be seeing these things coming didn't
see it coming why do you think that is
well as a basic idea in cognitive
science called situated cognition which
is that you are able to think and act in
the world because you have a semantic
structure that extends into the world so
right now you and I are interacting with
a screen as though it's real and we're
it situated in this face-to-face
dialogue with all with a huge global
infrastructure enabling it and the
situation structures are thinking so
what's happened is a lot of people are
in entrenched developmental pathways
where the development is constrained by
what the situation allows them to see
the feedbacks that are semantically
available or the incentive structures
that are semantically available and a
lot of them were constructive in ways
where there are levels of complexity
near levels of feedbacks that became
disconnected or or just never connected
in the first place so there's a kind of
obfuscation that's present the way that
I like to call this is there's a horizon
of ignorance complex systems have
obscurity in their very nature things
that are happening within a time frame
over here that happen another time frame
over here it's the time to communicate
the information is not in sync it's
obscure the system cannot see each part
and this is why the fragment
the reductionism the non holistic way
that our information Ecology's have been
built up historically make all of those
institutions blind and I know Daniel
Marton burgers spoken eloquently about
this so I won't say anymore except go
watch the interview on the one
sense-making but um but that is the
reality is the inability to achieve
collective intelligence is why those
institutions are failing so miserably
and this is why we also have this great
opportunity to sit alone in our homes
using zoom like you and I are right now
to create collective intelligence we can
actually create sense making systems
appropriate to our context without being
encumbered by the limits of those other
institutions because they're just not
working right there's been a lot of
people in the systems world who for
decades have been calling for change but
it's been a it's been boomeranging you
know the call for change seems to come
back every time we send it out it kind
of comes back and and that has been
because because there were so many
contexts coming together to form this
the the patterns that we've been stuck
in so if you think about it the
education system was really a
confirmation of the economic system the
economic system has really been a
confirmation of the education system and
these things are mirroring each other
and then the health system has been a
confirmation of the education system and
I recognize that the health systems are
different in different places but what
I'm getting at is that even the notion
of thinking about separating all the
different aspects of health right
there's a kind of reductionism that
medicine is premise upon which would be
okay if there was also this other place
where they put the whole thing back
together again
but where is the health you know and I
think right now we're starting to see
that some of these distinctions that
were made between but why would a virus
affect the education system why would a
virus stop the economic system that
should be something that is you know
stay in your lane virus you're supposed
to be a health issue not an economic
issue or a cultural issue or e is this
is this one of those moments where
actually the capacity that human beings
collectively hold for understanding
their world changes is this one of those
moments like are we at that one of those
junctions because this is a direct sort
of embodied experience of having to
connect with all our systems all you
mean yeah it's a directive however
embodied it is though it's entirely
possible not to see it though I don't
want to jump ahead and say everybody can
see the interdependency now because I
think that would be naive is there the
possibility that people could perceive
interdependence II now in a way that
they haven't yes absolutely and I would
add to that particularly the people who
have been most betrayed by the existing
system so if the ones I think that are
in the the greatest danger of
perpetuating old patterns are the people
who have profited from it we're at a
moment where there is a loosening of the
threads of old system patterns but
believe they want to tighten up they
want there is a call to return to
normalcy that is so strong it's it's
it's like wanting working with people
who are dealing with addiction and you
know that what it is that is known
is the state of being in that addictive
relationship and so this unknown state
is is not what anyone wants we don't
know how how do you survive in a world
with a broken economy how do you how do
you teach your kids who are you actually
if these institutions and structures
that your identity has been formed
within right you are your education
system you are your culture you are your
the health system your the dentistry the
write your religion your your your
economy your job right and if you don't
have those things if the world is
different in six months who-who are you
so it's scary and I think that the that
it would be I think it would be a
beautiful thing to have the people who
have been working in systems and
complexity for the last several decades
to actually come together now because
this this is a really important moment
and the systems were broken anyway
they've been broken why go back to
normal when you know I've seen this meme
everywhere when normals what got us here
normal was broken and that's how we
ended up here so so what can what can
this community of systems thinkers
actually bring that will help help
perception of that interdependence II be
a new normal so Nora also used the
analogy of addiction which Jordan Hall
did recently as well and I think it's a
really powerful way of looking at what's
going on that as a society if anyone's
up to be dealt with someone in it tried
to help an addict they'll know that
actually one of the big issues is
delusion its delusion walked thinking
and what we're going through now is this
kind of like as a society I think we've
been deluded for a long time and like
reality has really started to hit and so
this is something I think yeah I really
find that a useful metaphor yeah same I
think the addiction analogy is really
rich there's so much to it I think
another aspect of it is that really big
in the dynamics of addiction at least in
the twelve steps program is is the
dynamic of control what do we have
control over and what don't we have
control over and the whole point of an
addictive cycle and and having an
addiction is that you don't have control
over your behaviors even if you want to
stop and our society you know was you
know through you know you mentioned
delusion through momentum you know many
many other factors just kind of
rampaging forward in an unsustainable
way and
fascinating to me is this this hard stop
it reminds me of rock bottom in
addiction and now I've spoken to a few
people about this specifically and I
think the jury is still out on whether
this is rock bottom for society or
whether it's gonna take something even
more extreme to really hit that and
that's often a question in addiction
it's it's you know if you are with
someone going through that process it is
a question of oh I really I really
desperately hope this is rock bottom for
them so that they can really have that
that process and I hope that for our
current society and system but it
remains to be seen this is a beautiful
opportunity for those of us trying to
create the new economy but it's gonna be
a big shock to those who don't know the
economy shift so I think there are a lot
of aspects to this kind of flow this
reallocation of flow that none of us are
really prepared for except I'll make an
exception to that except those of us who
are learning how to do improv with
higher levels of human capacity which I
know you've talked a lot about a lot on
repre wisdom how to develop those human
capacities for dealing with uncertainty
for managing complexity for holding
different perspectives for improvising
in the moment for discerning reality all
of those skills are more important now
than ever but they're actually gonna
shift what the economy actually is in
the next weeks and the next months and
in the next years which is a collapse of
the old economy at least in part how
confident are you this I mean did you
want to explain more about that you see
that the collapse but when you say the
collapse of the economy most people will
sort of assume that's kind of an
end-of-the-world scenario well one thing
I would say is there was already an
end-of-the-world but most of us don't
remember it because it happened on
longer timescales so when we went from
living in hunter-gatherer societies to
eventually the majority of humans living
in cities or the span of about 10,000
years most of it happening in the last
500 then actually there was an end of
the world so there were several of them
and we've entered a new world that is
precarious super fragile and short-lived
but because most of us were born into it
it's what we believe is normal and it's
actually ephemeral this industrial
globalized fossil fuel based
civilization has only exactly existed
for two or three hundred years you might
build it up to five hundred years if you
want to say the first corporation in the
year 1500 and double-entry accounting in
the 14 70s and all of that but but some
on the last few hundred years which is a
blip and geologic timescales so what
most people don't realize is that the
economy that they think is going to
exist in the future is already dying or
dead but they're not able to update
their mental models because the patterns
are so subtle and diffuse and complex
and our education system has completely
failed to prepare them for this they are
not learning how to think this way and
so on so the economy that people are
afraid is going to die first of all it
already died for the majority of people
who here in numbers the 2008 financial
crash who recalls the movement from
full-time employment for a lifetime know
like I'm an IBM man in the 1950s to
everyone being a temp worker
those are collapses of the economy but
what's different about the collapse is
firstly it's a an interdependent of a
lot of collapses which makes it harder
to see but also we are in a process of
creating a mass extinction event you
know very very few people in ecology so
they don't understand what happens when
you take a complex food web and start
collapsing its web of connections so
instead of there being 12 layers of
relationships between species it
collapses to four crates for agility
across the whole system there when the
system collapses it takes down more
species humans are entangled in so many
food webs that attack has it's too
quickly into into
it will cause us to go extinct with it
and so aren't enough people who
understand ecology do you know how this
works to see that this is a real
possibility for our species in the next
50 to 100 years so our challenge is sort
of a spiritual or semantic challenge how
can we let go of our habits of normalcy
to practice discerning what is actually
real - then co-create the patterns that
give us the best chance of the future
that makes the planet livable for our
children and grandchildren this is what
the sustainability folks have been
saying for 50 years but it's most robust
articulations come out of complexity
science like mathematical biology
complex systems research pattern
formation phase transitions these things
from complexity science but it's the
same lesson so for the people who don't
know that the economy is dying or
already dead but they need to practice
is a little bit of Improv Theater to
practice putting themselves into
different social realities to learn how
to discern within it and also practice
cooperating because that's what they're
going to need to do moving forward and a
lot of people aren't going to get this
and they're gonna continue to be
disoriented and confused is there
anything else that's really burning
right now the thing that's burning right
now is the fierce urgency of now we have
this opportunity and if you watch the
people who play military games and
corporate takeover strategies and even
the sociopathic people who do and the
only clan called the Shock Doctrine of
grabbing resources when everyone's
confused they don't waste an opportunity
now those of us who care about life in
the future of the planet we waste a lot
of opportunities and what I would or
just to do is to not waste this one and
if you personally waste this one don't
reach the next one so I think that's
what I would say because these systems
and these patterns are intensifying
they're not easing up so whatever harms
are being done now we're setting the
stage for large
arms in the future simply by the dynamic
of continuing and so I'm as
uncomfortable as it may be to let
ourselves feel awkward and confused
that's exactly what we need to do to
learn new skills and to live differently
um and that's where this opportunity is
that we need to grab so I hope more
people do it yeah you talked about this
drive back to the status quo and they're
gonna be very very powerful actors on
that side trying to kind of patch up the
existing system we're talking probably
like mass government bailouts probably
dwarfing kind of the 2008 system so with
those really powerful actors on that
side what is the alternative to the new
normal but you're saying that it would
be great if the complexity thinkers and
the systems change people were involved
what what does that look like what does
a different system look like
I think that the better question is what
does it feel like what happened what
does it how does it think because the
what does it look like is going to be a
consequence of a whole lot of details
that get shifted from though the way it
feels or the way this that that there's
that the underlying premises so I'm not
in a rush to map out a vision of new
system I think that there's real
problems with doing that if you think
about the way soil works you know and
you think about the relationship between
the way so well is this combination of
relationships between bacteria between
nutrients between organisms between all
sorts of things happening that allow
other relationships to occur and those
relationships allow other relationships
to occur so somehow you get from the
soil to that person could be you or me
walking through the forest having an
idea okay so right now our trajectories
of causation and strategic planning and
envisioning don't work like that so that
that is where for me the most important
thing is this immediate notion of the
soil what relationships can be made
right now that be will be the
relationships that build more
relationships that lead to other
relationships that move across lots of
different contexts of being is that
clear or do you want me to spell that
out further maybe if you could unpack
that a little bit okay what does it mean
those
I mean it sounds like you're you're
describing an anti fragile system in a
way or inter system rather than a
extractive system but can you explain
what you mean by those relationships and
that context okay so if we take the soil
metaphor right you've got um you've got
these organisms under the ground and
then because of those organisms
there's the nutrients and the
possibility for the grass to grow or a
tree to grow and because the grass and
the tree and the the forest floor are
there it's possible for the birds to
have a place to be and because the birds
have a place to be it's possible for the
seeds to get dropped there that and then
go down into the soil that then make it
possible for the insects to be there
which in turn feed the birds right so
all of these relationships build
relationships and that's vitality okay
that's what vitality looks like we've
been in a world in which those
relationships have been cut
we haven't been interested in what were
the relationships that produced your
cellphone if I ask what are the
relationships that produce this little
piece of technology it's children who
have been working in slave conditions
that are sick it's it's incredible
poverty it's outrageous wealth gap it's
the deprivation and extraction and
destruction of of of soil of Earth of
right and then it's huge amounts of
petroleum is destruction of the of the
biosphere so this is the opposite
and what is happening in the compost
pile and therein lies the difference so
what I'm talking about is the perception
of interdependencies between different
aspects of your life and that the second
you start to actually be able to
perceive those interdependencies you're
going to behave different and that'll
change the way you are with your spouse
it'll change the way you think about
your body it'll change the way you think
about what it is you want from your life
it'll change the way you think about
what it means to be be a good person
how do you be a good person right what
does it mean to have a meaningful life
right now and how could we possibly
create a meaningful life that wasn't
built on destructive supply chains I
also
them for some concrete ideas like what
do we need to prepare for and where do
we go next
you've been very involved in the game be
the idea of sort of game be an
alternative operating system for society
do you think what's going on now makes
it more or less likely that that is a
possibility I believe much more likely
because part of the failure modes that
we saw across the world are examples of
things that have game be if we had a the
world had actually run by the game the
operating system may well have played
out very differently for instance one of
the kief holdings of game B is radical
transparency by government government
and Finance that there are no secrets
from the people other than a very few
military secrets and for instance this
whole damn thing could have been avoided
probably if it wasn't for corrupt lying
in China in the Wuhan province there was
a big political set of meetings that
were coming up in a couple of weeks and
you know the very human failure of not
wanting to look bad in front of your
peers led people in the Wuhan province
to cover up the the extent of this thing
for several weeks when it could have
been nipped in the bud and so radical
transparency could have prevented that
let's also look at the bad responses
across the West right nobody in the West
gets a gold star nobody even gets a
Silver Star
some countries deserve a brown star
leadership by the worst I don't know if
we have leadership by the worst but to
the first order we do
and again another foundational idea and
game be it sense making a collective
sense making Network sense making it's
unbelievable to me that the leadership
of the major Western countries did not
understand this the severity of this by
no later than the 20th of January in
reality their intelligence services were
providing them increasing risks of a
global pandemic from this Wuhan thing as
early as late December and the signal
was unbelievably clear by the 20th or
21st of January and yet United States
Italy UK Spain France
really started acting until at the ER at
the very earliest early March that was
five weeks as we talked about earlier
thinking about Exponential's we're
talking about something that let's say
in its native state seems to double
every three days three half-days let's
call it twice a week five weeks means
ten doublings what is 2 to the 10th 2 to
the 10th is a thousand why these things
are happens in because we do not have
good sense making and we do not have
good sense makers we have showman and
you know bullshit artists as our
political leaders right you know look at
the UK in the u.s. it's fine examples
right and those people are not sense
makers and nor have they build
administrations that know how to listen
carefully to the signal in the world
sift the signal from the noise and then
work on the on the signal and very
intelligently go from sense making to
decision making to action taking and we
just don't have a politics a political
system that creates leadership or
followers of those leaders who have that
sense making decision taking action
making potential wired in and that is
fundamental to the philosophy of game be
the other way treason game be would have
handled this way better is that one of
the things that we push strongly in the
game be world is that the theoretical
economic optimizations from the money
signal are a false signal because
they're all driven by short-term money
on money return and they cause the
system to under invest in robustness and
resilience they also cause long distance
lengths with a net very small but
positive economic return example I give
is you know fish caught in Northern
California gets sent to Florida to China
to be processed and then brought back to
the United States to be sold what the
hell right why because it's five cents
cheaper a pound but it exposes all that
protein to loss and a pandemic of this
sort
if we said we're not willing to give up
the resilience and robustness of having
our fish processed locally it would be a
very very small economic loss but a very
large gain in terms of resilience and
robustness and so game be inherently
thinks in terms of aggregate systems
attributes particularly resilience and
robustness further we strongly advocate
for localization where possible so that
an area you know a county or I'll call a
policy you know an area of about a
million people ought to be sort of
self-sufficient at least for 90 days
they don't have sufficient food stores
and have local energy generation but I
have fuel depots etc and it will cost a
little bit
the nominal dollar gdp by go down a
teeny bit but having that several nests
would be huge right now if we could have
said westchester county where the first
big outbreak in the United States
occurred shut it down snip all the
connections well guess what nothing bad
is gonna happen Westchester County is
self-sufficient if we could have just
called that play we probably could have
nipped it in the bud in the United
States and may have had to hit one or
two others but a consciously organized
bottom-up organization of society around
locate localism would have made managing
this way better on the other side there
I would say this pandemic has for me
heightened a possible flaw or shall we
say something we have not thought about
enough in Game B which is let's be
honest fair number the game P people are
kind of hippie-dippie types right quasi
anarchists you know really very
interested and let us do our own thing
and that's good in times of equilibrium
I believe it's the right way to think
plus or minus however a game be world
needs to be able to go into warfighting
mode when necessary and I've been
stating this for the last few weeks and
some people in the game B world of them
saying oh god damn that ruts turned into
an authoritarian what a motherfucker
right tough shit dudes social operating
systems that don't know
to boot into warfighting mode don't last
and one of the four fundamentals of game
be four fundamentals of game be our
self-organizing networks interest in a
decentralization and metastability
metastability means the system adjusts
itself so as to be able to last at least
in my version 500 years we believe game
a will collapse in the next before the
end of the century due to internal
contradictions and my point is if we
can't snap game B into warfighting mode
when necessary it will not be metastable
it will die and and keep in mind as we
talked to earlier we're on the fat tail
here but about here there are way worse
zombie apocalypses than this one
you know EMP attacks by rogue nations
solar flares that wipe out the grid you
know a small pox level pandemic and if
game B can't whip into warfighting mode
quickly it will fail and so in addition
to this decentralized more or less
consensus oriented bottom-up localism we
have to figure out how the signal can
percolate up in a play called and then
push back down in a way that people can
accept through sense making to lead to
coherent action in a war fighting mode
and as I said the the people who are
attracted to game be a lot of them just
react negatively to that but I say tough
shit dudes if you want game B to survive
it needs to be it needs to have the
ability to make a phase change into war
fighting mode when necessary and I'm
gonna spend at least some of my thoughts
over the next year on what needs to be
added to the game B synthesis to make it
capable of flipping States into a much
more coherent state when necessary the
analogy that I have used is that you
know when the caterpillar becomes a
butterfly at first turns to this this
couplet is liquid in the chrysalis that
when you know people are quick to toss
around this transformation word like
yeah we're just going to have
transformation really what they're
taught
King about is adjustment we're just
gonna adjust that caterpillar it's gonna
get some wings on it and that's gonna be
good to go
but that's not how it happens so
transformation really requires that let
liquefying and what comes out the other
side of it I think it would be foolish
to think that we can see that but what's
not foolish is to tend absolutely to the
details right now every tiny little move
matters everything we say matters
everything you do the way you treat
people the the the things you buy that
what you do with your day the way you
express something all of that in your
own little world matters so much because
it it is carrying the potentiality for
things that could change and thinks that
could not change so for me that's that's
I guess the most important thing is just
to tend every detail right now and hold
it open but hold it open in
interdependency and in care and in
really rigorous attention and not to get
not to get sloppy or greedy or grabby or
[Music]
scared to to be something you've never
been before do things you've never done
before
live in ways we've never lived before
you know who are you if you don't have
any money and you don't own anything who
are you in in your world so I think
that's a good
mental exercise if all the things that
the previous system has brought to you
or brought against you because that's
the other side of it or taken away who
would you be how would you be what's
essential in other words what's not
essential I like that you're framing it
within questions rather than answers
which I think as you've described this
as a liminal time I think it's a very
important thing to look at it's a
liminal time we're all in that state of
uncertainty and I think staying open to
that uncertainty is going to be the
important thing it's a rigorous thing
though it's not just a it's not just a a
meme right staying open to that
liminality is intense rigorous attention
and and and work to perceive multiple
contexts coming together to keep your
eyes open to pay attention to learn in
several different directions at the same
time to start to see patterns of
communication and to see the breakdowns
in those patterns to find the fluidity
and to feel it what's the what's the
tonality of it is it is it is it greedy
is it caring is it looking for
efficiency is it looking to nurture
right so these are the questions that
I'm working with right now what's being
revealed rebel wisdom was set up to make
sense of the world at a deeper level
than the mainstream media it was built
for these times of crisis and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times more
films and also for our rebel wisdom
members weekly sense-making calls with
our amazing interviewees and also we're
introducing the wisdom gym a place to
practice some of the skills that we've
talked about on the channel thanks for
watching and see you soon
[Music]